<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>GATOR Lab @ UF</title>
<link>https://gatorlab.io/posts.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://gatorlab.io/posts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<image>
<url>https://gatorlab.io/files/images/gator-logo-square-bg.png</url>
<title>GATOR Lab @ UF</title>
<link>https://gatorlab.io/posts.html</link>
<height>144</height>
<width>144</width>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.8.27</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>New dashboard for GIScience journal analysis</title>
  <dc:creator>Levente Juhasz</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gatorlab.io/posts/journal_dashboard/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="new-dashboard-for-journal-analysis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="new-dashboard-for-journal-analysis">New dashboard for journal analysis</h2>
<p>Building on the 2024 publication, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/13658816.2024.2347306">“Assessing publication trends in selected GIScience journals”</a> in IJGIS, the GATOR Lab is excited to release an interactive companion dashboard. This tool is designed to help the community navigate the evolving landscape of our field.</p>
<p>The dashboard provides a quantitative look at 24 core GIScience venues, tracking their evolution from 2018 through 2024 (with ongoing data updates in the future).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://gatorlab.io/files/images/giscience_collab_network.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:100.0%"></p>
<figcaption>International collaboration network in GIScience research</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="why-use-this" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-use-this">Why use this?</h3>
<p>Selecting a publication venue is often based on “gut feeling” or a single metric like Impact Factor. This tool allows for a more refined, multi-dimensional assessment of the field:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Meta Rankings</strong>: Compare journals using a composite index of eight different metrics (IF, CiteScore, SJR, SNIP, etc.) to see a more stable picture of “prestige”.</li>
<li><strong>Open Access Trends</strong>: Monitor the shift towards OA</li>
<li><strong>Collaboration Networks</strong>: Interactively explore how jurisdictions (countries) collaborate. Our data shows that while the field is growing, the Global South remains underrepresented… a gap we hope to highlight and help close to build an inclusive community.</li>
<li><strong>Cost vs.&nbsp;Impact</strong>: View the relationship between Article Processing Charges (APCs) and journal rankings to find the best “value” for your research.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="built-for-open-science" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="built-for-open-science">Built for Open Science</h3>
<p>In the spirit of open principles, the dashboard is built using <a href="https://posit-dev.github.io/r-shinylive/">Shinylive</a>. This means it runs entirely in your web browser via WebAssembly, which in turn requires no backend server or 3rd party resources. It is private, and permanently accessible. The initial Shiny dashboard is a reimplementation and expansion of the 2024 IJGIS article and it was built by <a href="https://gatorlab.io/people/students/corcino.html">Jorge Corcino</a>. Stay tuned as we are releasing the updated dataset and the source code of the dashboard very soon.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-word-to-the-wise" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-word-to-the-wise">A word to the wise</h3>
<p>We want to be clear about our view on using journal metrics to evaluate research impact. Quite frankly, we are not a fan of them. However, we need to be realistic and understand that it is a common practice in the academic community to use them. Think about going up for promotion, demonstrating the impact of your work, or justifying funding applications. Most of these decisions rely on some sort of metrics, and journal metrics are a common choice, so in a sense they are a necessary evil. While we may fundamentally disagree with putting to much emphasis on journal metrics, a lot of us are still at the mercy of them and therefore we are releasing this dashboard to build a better, more holistic understanding of the GIScience journal landscape.</p>
<p>On the bright side, better approaches to assess research impact are rapidly emerging, and we hope to see more of them in the future. A good resource to get started is the <a href="https://www.sfdeclaration.org/">San Francisco Declaration on Research Assessment</a> that recognizes and formalizes the need to improve the ways in which the outputs of scholarly research are evaluated.</p>
<p>With all its flaws, we still hope that our <a href="../../resources/journals.html">GIScience journal assessment dashboard</a> will serve as a useful resource for everyone from students selecting their first submission venue to senior researchers optimizing publication strategies to maximize the impact of their work.</p>
<p>Explore the dashboard <a href="../../resources/journals.html">here</a> or launch the <a href="../../resources/dashboard/index.html">Full Screen version</a>.</p>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://gatorlab.io/posts/journal_dashboard/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jan 2026 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gatorlab.io/files/images/giscience_journal_ranking_plot.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="171" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Welcome to the GATOR Lab!</title>
  <dc:creator>Levente Juhasz</dc:creator>
  <link>https://gatorlab.io/posts/welcome/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="hello-welcome" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hello-welcome">Hello &amp; Welcome!</h2>
<p>I am excited to announce the launch of the <strong>Geospatial Analytics, Technology and Open Research (GATOR) Lab</strong> at the University of Florida. I accepted a position of Assistant Professor of Geospatial Analytics in Geomatics from the Spring 2026 semester. This marks my return to UF after a 7-year spell at Florida International University as research faculty. I am beyond excited to be back at UF and to continue my research in geospatial analytics, technology and open research.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-gator" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-gator">Why GATOR?</h2>
<p>The GATOR acronym is a play on words. It stands for <strong>Geospatial Analytics, Technology and Open Research</strong>. It represents the <strong>G</strong>eospatial (or Geomatics), <strong>A</strong>nalytics, <strong>T</strong>echnology and <strong>O</strong>pen <strong>R</strong>esearch pillars of my research. As an alumnus, and now faculty member I also found it important to pay tribute to the Florida <strong>Gators</strong>🐊, and ground our lab’s mission within <strong>The Gator Nation</strong>.</p>
</section>
<section id="whats-ahead" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-ahead">What’s ahead?</h2>
<p>I am currently in the process of setting up our core infrastructure. The next and ongoing major step is to recruit. I am currently seeking <strong>two fully funded PhD students</strong> to join the lab. This is an exciting opportunity not only for me, but for the first few lab members, who will be an important part of establishing the lab’s culture and direction. I am not just looking for the usual candidates, but for people who are passionate about open science and eager to solve complex spatial problems through a data-science lens. While an excellent academic background is important, I am more interested in your intellectual curiosity and a critical mindset. I can’t stress the importance of this enough. Finding a mutual fit will make or break this experience. Committing to a long PhD program is a major decision. I want to commit to your future success as much as the success of the GATOR Lab, therefore, I am very intentional and selective about who I recruit. I expect you to be the same with making sure that the GATOR Lab and my mentorship are a good fit for you. With that being said, I am interested in the person behind the CV, and I am open to discussing your interests and aspirations. If you are interested in joining the lab, please consult the <a href="../../join.html">join</a> page for more information.</p>
<p>It is my hope that the lab will extend beyond PhD students. In the future, I plan to recruit postdocs, visiting scholars, and collaborators to push the boundaries of geospatial science. I am also interested in working with industry partners, and I am open to discussing potential collaborations, which will benefit the lab in many ways: it will inform our research, teaching, and help us stay at the cutting edge of geospatial analytics and technology.</p>
</section>
<section id="where-are-we-located" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="where-are-we-located">Where are we located?</h2>
<p>We are located in sunny South Florida, at the <a href="https://flrec.ifas.ufl.edu">Fort Lauderdale Research &amp; Education Center</a>. While not being located in Gainesville may seem unusual, it is a great location for research and collaboration. South Florida (Miami - Ft. Lauderdale - West Palm Beach) is a vibrant metropolitan area. It is a great place to be, and it also provides a great environment for research and collaboration: it is a hub of innovation and creativity, with a diverse population and a rich cultural heritage. It also lies at the forefront of man-made and environmental challenges waiting to be solved by science.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://gatorlab.io/posts/welcome/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://gatorlab.io/files/images/gator-logo-square.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
